<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The efficacy and extent of true purgation shewing I. What this operation is, not as vulgarly understood, II. How performed in human body, III. By what means fitly to be done, IV. When, how oft, and in what cases to be used, and what to be avoided, in this most frequent and helpful administration : distinguished from promiscuous evacuations, injuriously procured and falsely reputed purging / by Everard Maynwaringe, M.D.</title>
            <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31208</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11790823</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11790823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1488:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The efficacy and extent of true purgation shewing I. What this operation is, not as vulgarly understood, II. How performed in human body, III. By what means fitly to be done, IV. When, how oft, and in what cases to be used, and what to be avoided, in this most frequent and helpful administration : distinguished from promiscuous evacuations, injuriously procured and falsely reputed purging / by Everard Maynwaringe, M.D.</title>
                  <author>Maynwaringe, Everard, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Browne ..., and R. Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Laxatives.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49195:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49195:1"/>
            <p>THE Efficacy and Extent OF TRUE PURGATION. SHEWING,
<list>
                  <item>I. What this <hi>Operation</hi> is; not as Vulgarly underſtood.</item>
                  <item>II. How Performed in <hi>Human</hi> Body.</item>
                  <item>III. By what <hi>Means</hi> fitly to be done.</item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>When;</hi> How <hi>oft;</hi> and in what <hi>Caſes</hi> to be uſed: And what to be <hi>avoided;</hi> in this moſt <hi>frequent,</hi> and <hi>helpful</hi> Adminiſtration.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Promiſcuous</hi> Evacuations; <hi>iujuriouſly</hi> procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and <hi>falſly</hi> reputed PURGING.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>EVERARD MAYNWARINGE,</hi> M. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. Browne,</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr;</hi> and <hi>R. Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> near St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleet ſtreet,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49195:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49195:2"/>
            <head>THE Efficacy and Extent OF TRUE PURGATION.</head>
            <p>OF all the Phyſical <hi>Operations</hi> in Order to Curing; and to prevent Diſeaſes approaching or feared; <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is the moſt <hi>general, uſeful,</hi> and <hi>advantagious:</hi> For this alone, being well and truly performed, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom fails to give good Relief, and great Aſſiſtance; in <hi>most,</hi> and <hi>almoſt all</hi> the Complaints of diſeaſed, and infirm <hi>Bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is; that this <hi>Operation</hi> is ſo frequently appointed, and uſed by all <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> in their Undertakings of the <hi>Sick;</hi> as moſt neceſſarily required, in the various Methods, and Deſigns of Curing: The <hi>Energy</hi> and <hi>Effects</hi> whereof are ſo conducing to <hi>Cures;</hi> that look through the whole <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Diſeaſes, and their <hi>Methods</hi> uſed, in any of the great <hi>Practical</hi> Authors; you will rarely find <hi>Purgation</hi> omitted: But on the contrary; more often repeated, and inſiſted on, than any other <hi>Operation</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Phyſick.</p>
            <p>And moſt <hi>People</hi> of their own Inclination, and Choice; have Recourſe to this <hi>Help</hi> (without the Advice of a Phyſician) when they find themſelves, heavy and indiſpoſed; full at <hi>Stomach;</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite abated; reſtleſs, or pained in any Part. And in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; they deſign rationally, and well for themſelves; but they <hi>miſs</hi> it, in the Performance; not knowing with <hi>What,</hi> or <hi>How</hi> to do this Work, as it ought to be done: For, of all the <hi>Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> procured by Phyſick, none ſo much abuſed and miſtaken,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49195:3"/>as <hi>Purgation;</hi> not only by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilful</hi> in this Art; but alſo by the <hi>Learned;</hi> as appears upon the Enquiry and Examination anon.</p>
            <p>Indeed, there are many ſufficient Reaſons; why <hi>Purgation</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>frequently</hi> uſed, and confided in for Help in various Caſes; both as <hi>Preventive</hi> and <hi>Curative</hi> means.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> Becauſe <hi>Nature</hi> in her common Courſe, daily requires <hi>Evacuation</hi> that way; is thereby unloaded and alleviated by ſuch diſcharge of the excremental <hi>Faeces;</hi> which if they are retained beyond due Time, and longer than uſual; <hi>Man</hi> is not ſo light, eaſie, and pleaſant; but finds ſome Alteration and Diſcompoſure in the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> Diſeaſes take their <hi>Riſe,</hi> more often from depraved Matter, the Relicts of vitiated Digeſtions; not being duly ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and ſent away by <hi>Stool;</hi> but remaining in the lower Region of the Body, infeſting thoſe <hi>Offices</hi> and depraving the nutrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Juices which ſupply the Bloud: From hence, the <hi>vital</hi> Stream becomes degenerate and impure; producing various Diſeaſes, and <hi>ſymptomatical</hi> Appearances in divers Parts of the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Nature by her own <hi>Effort</hi> and Abilitity to ſtrive; more often frees her ſelf, from the Oppreſſion of peccant Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by caſting it forth at the <hi>Back</hi>-Door; than by any other way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly;</hi> A Purgative <hi>Operation</hi> leads foremoſt, and begins the <hi>Method</hi> regularly in moſt Caſes (very few excepted:) And is more often repeated than any other <hi>Operation,</hi> by the <hi>Learned</hi> and moſt <hi>Experienced</hi> Practiſers: For if the Diſeaſe do not lye <hi>(in primis viis)</hi> in the <hi>Stomach, Pancreas, Meſentery,</hi> or <hi>Guts;</hi> but ſeated in ſome remoter Part; yet the lower Region of the Body muſt firſt be unloaded, and the foulneſs of thoſe <hi>Parts</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſed; before Medicine can arrive at the Part <hi>remotely</hi> affected: Which being well performed; you may then hopefully expect, what other <hi>Medicinal</hi> Operation the Caſe may properly require, will be effectual; (if farther Proſecution be neceſſary) having thus far rightly proceeded, and laid a good Foundation for Cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Purgation being in Imitation of <hi>Nature</hi>'s Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; or an <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of Nature to do that Work effectually, where in ſhe hath been deficient; is probably and rationally the beſt <hi>Operation,</hi> to reſtore her into the Rectitude of Government; for a due execution of all the <hi>Bodily</hi> Functions.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49195:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly;</hi> True Purgation is ſo <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſive;</hi> ſo powerful and prevailing in its Operation; that it checks and abates Diſeaſes conſiderably, acting <hi>alone,</hi> by its ſingle Virtue and Power: And ſometimes does perform the <hi>whole</hi> Work, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more is needful to be done. And farther; this <hi>Operation,</hi> being ſeaſonably and duly made uſe of; is the beſt <hi>Preventive</hi> to keep of Diſeaſes; and to <hi>Preſerve</hi> Bodies in a good ſtate of Health.</p>
            <p>Since <hi>Purgation</hi> is of ſuch Importance; ſo neceſſarily required in the <hi>Cure</hi> of Diſeaſes; and alſo for <hi>Preſervation</hi> from Diſeaſes: You are then rightly to underſtand,
<list>
                  <item>1. What this <hi>Purgation</hi> is; in its proper ſignification, and the true <hi>Operation</hi> thereof.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>How,</hi> or after <hi>what</hi> Manner, it is performed in the Body.</item>
                  <item>3. By what fit <hi>Means</hi> or <hi>Medicines,</hi> it ought to be done; that truly and fully anſwers, the Intention of this moſt effectual <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. When ſeaſonably and fitly, <hi>Purgation</hi> is to be uſed: And what <hi>Contraindications</hi> do forbid it.</item>
                  <item>5. What <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and <hi>Caſes</hi> do require it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Purgation,</hi> by the Import of the Word, is <hi>Purification;</hi> and <hi>Purging</hi> is <hi>Purifying.</hi> That is a ſeparating, and cleanſing away of impure, feculent, and preternatural Matter, that vitiates and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praves the nutritious <hi>Juices;</hi> and is unfit for the Service of the Body. And without ſuch <hi>Purification,</hi> there is no true <hi>Purgation;</hi> but the Operation <hi>fruſtrate;</hi> as not effecting what it was intended for. Therefore all <hi>Evacuations,</hi> procured by Phyſick at the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament; are not <hi>Purging</hi> properly and truly: But which are ſo performed, as to <hi>depurate,</hi> and render the Body more <hi>clean, ſound,</hi> and <hi>wholeſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> I ſhall make ſome <hi>Obſervations,</hi> as cautio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and uſeful; to diſtinguiſh the <hi>Abuſes</hi> and <hi>Counterfeits,</hi> from true and effectual Purgation.</p>
            <p>That a number of <hi>Stools</hi> procured by Phyſick, does not always perform the <hi>Intention</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> of Purgation; nor is benefit to be expected thereby: But ſuch an <hi>Evacuation</hi> as is promoted by <hi>wholeſom</hi> good Medicine; cauſing a gentle fermenting <hi>Secretion,</hi> and <hi>ſeparation</hi> of peccant unſerviceable Matter, calmly ſending it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49195:4"/>forth. This is the only <hi>Purging</hi> that gives <hi>Relief;</hi> and great <hi>Benefit</hi> will follow from ſuch amicable <hi>Operations,</hi> in moſt Caſes that preſent: And by <hi>Purgation</hi> after this manner (though often repeated) Nature is not impaired or weakened; but <hi>alleviated,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, and more able.</p>
            <p>But by forced <hi>promiſcuous</hi> Evacuations; hurrying out all that lies in the way, both good and bad together; though the Body is unloaded thereby, and perhaps ſome <hi>good</hi> may be done by <hi>chance;</hi> but more certainly ſome <hi>Hurt;</hi> and probably this hath the greater ſhare, in ſuch rude <hi>Operations,</hi> as often it falls out ſo: For, after thoſe <hi>churliſh</hi> Doſes, made up of <hi>malign</hi> Ingredients; the pale thin <hi>Faces</hi> do appear, to teſtifie how <hi>ill</hi> they have been treated in Phyſick: But they let fly <hi>luſtily,</hi> and <hi>Fools</hi> think that was <hi>bravely,</hi> having forgot the <hi>Gripes</hi> and the ſick Fits; thinking it was all as it ſhould be; and do not ſuſpect any miſchief done thereby: But they will find the <hi>Effects</hi> afterwards; and muſt take <hi>Phyſick</hi> again, for the Diſeaſe of <hi>Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many People eſteem their <hi>Purging</hi> Medicine, by the Number of <hi>Stools:</hi> If it works half a <hi>ſcore,</hi> or <hi>dozen</hi> Times; then they have made a good Day's Work; and think their Time and Money well beſtowed. But a Medicine that operates, but four or five times in a Day; they make no Account of; and have not Patience to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute their Diſeaſes with ſuch flow <hi>Purgers:</hi> They muſt have their Buſineſs done ſpeedily, and probably that's the way, not to have it done; for commonly, and in this caſe eſpecially; the more <hi>Haſte,</hi> the worſe <hi>Speed.</hi> For if <hi>Purgation</hi> be a <hi>fermentative</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, procuring a Secretion; Reaſon and Experience tells, that is not a quick, haſty Work. They don't conſider, and they have not been well taught; that <hi>gentle</hi> Purging, and <hi>oftner</hi> taking; deliberately and gradually collecting depraved Matter; and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidly conveying it forth by wholeſome good Medicine; this is the moſt <hi>hopeful,</hi> and <hi>helpful</hi> Operation.</p>
            <q>Eradicativa Evacuatio, optimè per plures Evacuationes Minora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivas perficitur.</q>
            <p>Therefore when much emptying, and many <hi>Stools</hi> are required, to compleat the Work of <hi>Purgation;</hi> let that <hi>Operation</hi> be gentle, and repeated the more often (with Intermiſſion and Reſpite) until <hi>Purification</hi> be perfected: In ſo doing, the <hi>Life</hi> will not be tired and weakened; nor the <hi>Body</hi> exhauſted and impaired; by ſuch gradual ſelecting, and moderate diſcharging of unſerviceable Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter only.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49195:4"/>
               <head>After what manner <hi>PURGATION</hi> is performed in the <hi>BODY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It was the Opinion of the <hi>Ancients;</hi> and ſo continued by many at this time; that <hi>Purgatives</hi> operate <hi>(electivè)</hi> by attracting this or that Humor peculiarly; and that by their different <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal</hi> Propriety and <hi>specific</hi> Qualities, they do attract <hi>(Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patheticè)</hi> a different Humor or Matter: Some <hi>Water,</hi> others <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler;</hi> ſome draw out <hi>Phlegm,</hi> others <hi>Melancholy.</hi> Thus <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> taught; from which Judgment, diverſity of Purging Medicines have been contrived, to fit ſeveral Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as they ſuppoſe.) Some Bodies abounding with <hi>Choler,</hi> others with <hi>Phlegm,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore it was thought reaſonable, that Purging Medicines ſhould be divers: And from hence the reputed <hi>Purgatives</hi> have been diſtinguiſhed and diſtributed into ſeveral Claſſes: <hi>Phlegmagoga, Cholagoga, Melanagoga, Hydragoga</hi> All which will appear but an Accumulation of Errours. <hi>Dato uno abſurdo; multa exinde conſequuntur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contrary to this Opinion; <hi>Paracelſus, Joubertus,</hi> and others, have aſſerted; Purging Medicines to operate <hi>(per Antipathiam)</hi> in a hoſtile manner; that they do proſecute, expel and drive out noxious <hi>Humors,</hi> as having Enmity therewith, and performing after the manner of <hi>Alexipharmacals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But neither of theſe <hi>Opinions</hi> will ſtand good upon Examination and ſtrict Enquiry; as having no ſound Foundation to ſupport either of them; but involved with many Difficulties, as not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally to be maintained: Notwithſtanding, upon ſuch ſuppoſed Truths; pretended <hi>Purgative</hi> Operations hath been deſigned and grounded thereon, to the Prejudice of <hi>Millions</hi> of People: For, if manifeſt <hi>Evacuation</hi> were but procured, by the common injurious Means; it always paſſed currently for <hi>Purgation;</hi> not being able to diſcern and diſtinguiſh, between <hi>Evacuating</hi> promiſcuouſly, and <hi>Purging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The two former <hi>Opinions</hi> being ſet aſide; I ſhall produce a <hi>third,</hi> more rational, and clearer from Intanglements.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Purgation</hi> being an Operation, imitating Nature in her ordinary daily courſe; ſetting forth the <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of natural Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuations; illuſtrates and declares the Manner of <hi>Purgation</hi> artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially procured by Medicine.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49195:5"/>
               <p>Food received into the Stomach, is there digeſted by <hi>Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> into a Chyle or Juice; then ſent out into the <hi>Guts:</hi> where the Alimentary Part thereof, is conveyed by proper Veſſels, for the uſe and ſupply of the Body: The excrementitious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable Part, is carried down for expulſion. The motion for conveyance out of the <hi>Stomach,</hi> is performed by <hi>Fibers</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting and compreſſing that <hi>Bag;</hi> the lower Orifice of the <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach</hi> then opens, and tranſmits into the <hi>Guts;</hi> where alſo the <hi>Fibers</hi> of the <hi>Inteſtines</hi> contracting, do cauſe a <hi>vermicular</hi> motion, protruding the Contents from Part to Part, until the <hi>Faces</hi> arrive at the Fundament for excretion. Thus much only in ſhort, which at large might be ſet forth, if neceſſary.</p>
               <p>In like manner <hi>Purgation</hi> is performed (but more vigorouſly, and oftner evacuating) which is a Repetition of doing Nature's Work, to perfect by <hi>Medical</hi> Aſſiſtance, what could not be done without ſuch Help. A <hi>Purgative</hi> Medicine being received into the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, cauſeth a <hi>Fermentation</hi> there; raiſing up indigeſted <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts,</hi> and ſubſiding depraved Matter, cleaving to the corrugated <hi>Tunicles</hi> of the <hi>Ventricle;</hi> and puts it upon motion to be ſent downwards into the <hi>Guts;</hi> there to be diſtributed as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>But this is not All; <hi>Purgation</hi> extends yet farther: For, the <hi>Stomach</hi> being the <hi>Center</hi> of the <hi>Life,</hi> where the <hi>Regimen</hi> of the Body is more eminently managed; this principle Part; or rather the Principle of Human Nature, being there affected with the <hi>Purgative;</hi> cauſeth the whole Body to be drawn into Conſent and Co-operation; by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Identity,</hi> of the ubiquitary vital Principle: So that this depurating <hi>Fermentation</hi> is promoted by the <hi>Life,</hi> in all the <hi>Veins</hi> and <hi>Arteries;</hi> ſome Branches whereof, having their Inſertions into the cavity of the <hi>Guts;</hi> impure and uſeleſs Matter is brought from all Parts, to be diſcharged into the <hi>Kennel,</hi> or Sink of the Body, and ſent forth by that commom Outlet, the <hi>Fundament.</hi> Thus the whole Maſs of <hi>Bloud,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecated and cleared, from <hi>heterogeneous</hi> Admixture, by <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> after this manner performed, and not by <hi>Attraction,</hi> as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuppoſed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Regimen</hi> of the <hi>Life,</hi> is not always neceſſitated and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to viſible <hi>Organs;</hi> but acts ſometimes <hi>influentially,</hi> without viſible corporeal <hi>Mediums;</hi> and therefore in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of Human Nature, many Actions are performed at diſtance, without the connexion of <hi>Tubes</hi> or Veſſels for conveyance. But our tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49195:5"/>Learning gives no ſuch Information; and therefore extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Enquiries have been made in <hi>Anatomy</hi> (where it is not to be found) that they may render an Account of ſuch <hi>internal</hi> Operations; as they can give no Reaſon for otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Thus they would have the World believe; that by an exact Knowledge in <hi>Anatomy;</hi> ſatisfactory Accounts may be given, for all the preternatural <hi>Phoenomena,</hi> and Defections of Human Nature: And how Medicine is tranſmitted, to operate upon every Part of the Body. But herein they are more induſtrious for ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves to talk <hi>finely;</hi> than to deſign curing <hi>ſucceſsfully:</hi> Or give the true Account of <hi>Diſeaſes;</hi> and how curing is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Body: Forgetting, or neglecting this Axiom; <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura eſt Morborum Medicatrix:</hi> (And ſometimes <hi>Morborum Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrix</hi>) which cauſed a Reproof from an intelligent <hi>Obſervator,</hi> for their over-Curioſity and expence of Time in Diſſections. <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiebat namque pro Anatome; ſitum, colligationem, &amp; uſus Partium: Non autem tota vita Cadaverum Lani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nam, ad minimae venae ductus inveniendos, exercuiſſe.</hi> Joan. Van Helmont.</p>
               <p>The denominating Principal Part of Human Nature (the <hi>Regent</hi> vital <hi>Spirit,</hi> that makes, mends, and maintains Bodies) hath not been regarded and enquired into as ought; being the <hi>Efficient</hi> and <hi>Rector</hi> of all Human Actions; internal and external; both in the ſtate of <hi>Health,</hi> and <hi>Sickneſs.</hi> But they think themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, no farther than <hi>Humors,</hi> and <hi>Organs;</hi> and by them to ſet forth a full Account of Humanity, and <hi>morbous</hi> Alterations; as alſo the manner of Curing.</p>
               <p>Purgative <hi>Fermentation</hi> begun in the <hi>Stomach,</hi> is promoted through the Body; not by Conſent of <hi>Parts,</hi> and Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by <hi>Veſſels</hi> of Conveyance, as vulgarly ſo accounted: But <hi>(per Identitatem Medii)</hi> by Continuity and Unity of the <hi>Life;</hi> ſpreading and reſiding in every Part of the Body. From whence it is; that the <hi>Life</hi> being touched in the <hi>Center,</hi> with a fermenting <hi>Purgative</hi> Virtue; is alſo affected likewiſe, to the <hi>Confines</hi> of vital Government. But the common Learning does not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and teach any Communication or Conveyance; but by viſible <hi>Ductures</hi> and <hi>Conduits,</hi> tranſmitting from Part to Part.</p>
               <p>That this may not ſeem ſtrange; but probable and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, for <hi>Nature</hi> (the <hi>Life</hi>) to operate after ſuch a ſecret man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; take theſe following Examples as parallel, to confirm the Verity thereof. The firſt an <hi>Operation</hi> artificially procured by Medicament, for <hi>Purification:</hi> The latter, meerly natural
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49195:6"/>and ſpontaneous by <hi>Aliment,</hi> for Refection and Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A <hi>Sudorifick</hi> Medicine being received into the Stomach; the virtue thereof is diffuſed ſometimes in an hour, or two; and affects the whole Body; cauſing a moiſt <hi>Tranſpiration</hi> in every Part: And this muſt be by <hi>Irradiation,</hi> not by a long paſſage of <hi>Circulation,</hi> through viſible <hi>Ductures</hi> of Conveyance: For, it cannot rationally be ſuppoſed, that in ſo ſhort ſpace of Time; the Medicine can be carried <hi>materially</hi> into every Part of the Body; but is <hi>virtually</hi> conveyed, by <hi>influencial</hi> Power of the vital regent Principle; reſiding in the <hi>Stomach,</hi> (there <hi>eminenter</hi>) and praeſiding over all the <hi>Faculties.</hi> And to perform this Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, there needs no Veſſels of Conveyance out; becauſe the whole Body is prompt and ready, for ſuch a <hi>vaporous</hi> Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: <hi>Totum corpus eſt perſpirabile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. When a Perſon is faint and feeble by too long faſting; <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> then received into the <hi>Stomach;</hi> enlivens and ſtrengthens all <hi>Parts</hi> immediately (long before the <hi>Food</hi> can be diſtributed through the Body) and only by refreſhing the <hi>Life</hi> in the <hi>Center:</hi> Such <hi>radiant</hi> Influence ſtreams from thence, as to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the whole Body. So <hi>Purgative</hi> Virtue is diffuſed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated from the <hi>Stomach;</hi> cauſing a <hi>fermentative</hi> motion in the <hi>Veins</hi> and <hi>Arteries;</hi> arriving therein much ſhorter Time, than with common Conveyance by the known <hi>Veſſels;</hi> which would be long and tedious to expect.</p>
               <p>Hence it does appear, how <hi>Purgative</hi> Fermentation is raiſed, and extended at diſtance <hi>influent ially,</hi> by conduct and co-opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Life;</hi> without viſible <hi>Ductures:</hi> But the feculent Matter ſeparated for <hi>Excretion,</hi> is exported manifeſtly by <hi>Veſſels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this <hi>Doctrine</hi> you may underſtand; that the World hath been deceived in the great Buſineſs of <hi>Purgation:</hi> For, <hi>Practiſers</hi> not having a right <hi>Notion</hi> thereof in the manner of <hi>Performance</hi> in the Body; they could not well adapt a <hi>Purgative</hi> Medicine for the true Execution of that <hi>Operation:</hi> And Failure therein, hath given great <hi>Delays</hi> and <hi>Diſappointments,</hi> in the Practice of Phyſick: Foraſmuch as true <hi>Purgation</hi> contributes mainly in the cure of all Diſeaſes, ariſing <hi>from,</hi> or depending <hi>upon</hi> depraved <hi>humoral</hi> Matter; and gives the deepeſt <hi>ſtroak,</hi> in eradicating the <hi>Seminaries</hi> thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49195:6"/>
               <head>By what means True <hi>PURGATION</hi> is to be Effected.</head>
               <p>Since it is manifeſt, that <hi>Purgation</hi> operates by <hi>Fermentation</hi> to produce <hi>Purification:</hi> Then we are to enquire, what <hi>Properties</hi> a Medicine is to be endowed with, that <hi>really</hi> and <hi>effectually</hi> can perform that Work.</p>
               <p>The primitive <hi>Profeſſors</hi> having no <hi>Guide</hi> to direct, nor <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps</hi> to trace and follow; but making the firſt Attempts in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning <hi>Purgation;</hi> did venture upon divers <hi>Experiments;</hi> and what raiſed a Diſturbance in the Body, forcing <hi>Nature</hi> to expel downwards and evacuate; was then noted for a <hi>Purgative.</hi> The Ancients, as <hi>Hippocrates, Galen,</hi> &amp;c. coming after the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors: They reviſed thoſe rough inartificial <hi>Exemplars;</hi> and produced ſomething better: And <hi>Modern</hi> Practiſers have made ſome Amendments; but fall ſhort of compleating <hi>true Purgative</hi> Medicines: That we can only ſay; the latter <hi>Inventions</hi> are not ſo <hi>bad</hi> as the <hi>firſt;</hi> or what they were a <hi>Thouſand</hi> Years ago; but not what they ought to be now.</p>
               <p>If a <hi>placid</hi> and <hi>benign</hi> Fermentation, is praevious; the direct and only way to deſign <hi>Purgation,</hi> which is <hi>Purification:</hi> Then no Medicine compoſed of <hi>virulent,</hi> or <hi>malign</hi> Ingredients; is a proper and fit <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to perform that Work: Nor is it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to expect ſo <hi>good</hi> an Effect, ſhould be wrought by ſuch <hi>bad</hi> Means. We may from hence conclude; that all thoſe <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> (ſo called) which in their Nature have <hi>malign</hi> injurious Qualities to Human Bodies; are improper and miſtaken to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch an Operation as <hi>Purging;</hi> which is <hi>Purifying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we are to examine, the common reputed <hi>Purgatives;</hi> ſo much eſteemed, and ſo often uſed, by <hi>Practiſers</hi> in this Age; that we may ſee how far they anſwer the <hi>Title</hi> given: Whether they be <hi>innocent, wholeſom,</hi> and <hi>harmleſs;</hi> as true <hi>Purgatives</hi> ought: Or otherwiſe; affecting the Body with their <hi>ill</hi> Qualities, and operating by ſtimulating and <hi>noxious</hi> Impreſſions upon the <hi>Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Number of common reputed Purgatives, are: <hi>Euphorbium, Scammony, Colloquintida, Hellebore, Elaterium, Jallap, Briony, Gutta Gamandrae, Turbith, Sena,</hi> &amp;c. many others: Wherein there are <hi>degrees</hi> of Badneſs; ſome not ſo miſchievous as others are: But none to be called <hi>wholeſom</hi> and purely <hi>good;</hi> but what hath ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49195:7"/>ill <hi>Quality</hi> injurious to <hi>Human</hi> Nature: And are not what true <hi>Purgatives</hi> ought to be; which I ſhall prove,
<list>
                     <item>1. By the manner of their <hi>Operations.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. By their <hi>Effects.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. By the <hi>Account</hi> given of them, from <hi>Authentic</hi> Writers, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> and <hi>Modern.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Operation of <hi>common</hi> Purgatives, is uſually attended with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſineſs, Dullneſs,</hi> and <hi>Laſſitude; nauſeating,</hi> or <hi>vomiting;</hi> grinding or griping <hi>Pains;</hi> exhauſting <hi>Evacuations</hi> and <hi>Excoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; raking,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>racking</hi> the Bowels: Some of theſe at leaſt; and ſometimes all of theſe, are concomitant Symptoms: Which do manifeſt their diſcordant, and <hi>malign</hi> Properties; ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical and deſtructive to <hi>Human</hi> Nature.</p>
               <p>Few there are that have been uſed to <hi>Phyſick;</hi> but can atteſt ſome Part hereof, by their own <hi>Experience:</hi> And ſome of them, will tell <hi>dreadful</hi> Stories; how they have been abuſed by <hi>purging</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly:</hi> The ill <hi>Effects</hi> wrought from virulent Impreſſions of the common reputed <hi>Purgatives,</hi> that pervert the Digeſtions, and vitiate the Blood: They do not appear preſently, but ſome Time after; and then not ſuſpected, from whence or what Cauſe, ſuch Alterations do come: For, after the irkſom <hi>Operation</hi> is over; the next Day, perhaps, the Patient Sufferer is more at eaſe; and then begins to have a good <hi>Opinion</hi> of his Purge (when the Storm is over) and ſays it has done him good. And I can tell how much good that is: The Body being unloaded thereby; and probably ſome of the <hi>morbific</hi> Matter complained of, may be carried out, (if it lie in the way ready for Paſſage;) and this makes a mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of former <hi>Pains,</hi> and at preſent the <hi>Patient</hi> is better. And this is the beſt of it, that can be told: Which happens but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times: As when the diſeaſed Perſon is <hi>ſtrong</hi> and able to bear bad Medicines; and the cauſe of Complaint not ſo conſiderable, as to require much Phyſick.</p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> be great; radicated and ſtubborn to yield; that there is need of repeated, and often <hi>Purgations:</hi> Then, and in ſuch Caſes; the common <hi>Purges,</hi> do ſhew their <hi>Hostility</hi> to Human Nature; leaving the Characters of their <hi>Malignity</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them. Such as are ſo engaged into a Courſe of <hi>Phyſick;</hi> change their former Countenance, for <hi>pale, thin</hi> Chaps: Strength wears
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49195:7"/>away, and feeble <hi>Legs</hi> are the effects of that kind of <hi>Purging.</hi> So it is with the ſtronger fort; that are able to walk about, when their Diſeaſe makes a Ceſſation.</p>
               <p>And if you count the Number of thoſe that receive <hi>no Benefit;</hi> but are rather worſe; you will find them to be many: As when the Patient is <hi>Sick</hi> and <hi>weak;</hi> that wants a true <hi>Purgative,</hi> a Medicine extraordinary good; or no good to be done otherwiſe: Then in ſuch caſes, the common <hi>Purges</hi> ſets the <hi>Sick</hi> and <hi>Feeble</hi> forward, towards their long Home. But ſuch as do recover (by good <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi>) from Sickneſs, and ſeemingly are well; and have eſcaped the evil of bad <hi>Purgatives</hi> at preſent: Yet all the miſchief is not paſt; there comes an after Reckoning to account for: The Relicks and Impreſſions of your <hi>virulent Purges,</hi> hath laid the Foundation of another Diſeaſe, which you will hear of in a little time; and you cannot imagine how it ſhould come.</p>
               <p>Moſt People have this Apprehenſion, that <hi>Purging Phyſick</hi> is next to Poyſon; and therefore if it does not work, they are dreadfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; and well they may: But if it does operate; then they think all is well enough: but not ſo ſafe as they think: For tho' there be <hi>Evacuation</hi> ſufficient, as to the number of Stools; yet the <hi>Taint</hi> impreſſed upon the Body, both continent and contained; and alſo upon the <hi>Life,</hi> to alienate and infect the <hi>Regent</hi> Spirit: There muſt be a Depravation from thence; the effects whereof will not be ſmothered; though the cauſe you do not imagine, when thoſe effects do appear, a good while after: For, although ſome part of the <hi>Purgative Venom,</hi> comes away by <hi>Stool</hi> the Day of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation;</hi> yet there is a Remainder that infects the <hi>Bloud,</hi> and will produce various ill effects, in divers parts of the Body.</p>
               <p>That it does mix with the <hi>Bloud,</hi> and by that vehicle is carried into all parts of the Body: I find a late Author of the ſame Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; where he ſaith,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Extra dubium ponatur, Medicamenti Purgantis corpuſcula quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam in ſanguinem admitti, perque totum ejus liquorem diffundi.<bibl>D. Willis.</bibl>
                  </q>
And ſoon after theſe words do follow:
<q>Quippe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe erit quaſdam Cathartici particulas, ſucco nutricio permiſtas, per vaſa lactea obrepere. <bibl>Idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſince it is ſo; that the <hi>Purgative</hi> Venom commixeth with the <hi>Bloud,</hi> and therewith runs through the whole Body; how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and fearful ought People to be in the matter of <hi>Purgation:</hi> But when the ill effects of former <hi>Purgatives</hi> do bud forth, they have no other Remedy, but to the ſame, and ſuch like Purges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49195:8"/>They know not how to get better; they are ſuch as the <hi>Shop's</hi> are furniſh'd with; and ſuch as are <hi>Preſcribed</hi> to the <hi>Shops,</hi> upon all occaſions. What do you think will be the <hi>end</hi> of ſuch Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulation of Errours? or how ſoon the <hi>end</hi> may come?</p>
               <p>Here by the way, I muſt <hi>Remark,</hi> and ſet down this injurious <hi>Repetition,</hi> for one eminent cauſe, of Man's infirm diſeaſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and conſequently hath contributed much, to the Abbrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life; and the Off-ſpring in Ages to come, will degenerate yet more, and be of ſhorter Duration; being deſcended from ſuch depraved Progenitors.</p>
               <p>Is it reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that one <hi>virulent</hi> Medicine; ſhould raſe out the <hi>Impreſſions</hi> of another, that went before? If the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xioms</hi> be true; <hi>Natura eſt Morborum Medicatrix:</hi> We cannot in Reaſon think, that Nature will, or can work with ſuch bad Tools: <hi>Purification</hi> cannot be effected, by depraving and corrupting Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</p>
               <p>And the fore-named <hi>Author;</hi> giving an Account of <hi>Purgation;</hi> yields in a great meaſure, to this cenſure of Purgatives: <q>Nec enim de nihilo eſt quod vulgus adeo pertimeſcat, ſi quando Medice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men minus operetur; ne virulentia exinde contracta, &amp; derelicta, poſt quam diu in corpore delituit, tandem aliquando affectus malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos produceret: a tali namque occaſione, interdum pathemata quaſi leproſa excitantur. <bibl>D. Willis.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>It is not without cauſe, that People are afraid, when their <hi>Purge</hi> works not ſufficiently; leaſt the <hi>virulency</hi> thence contracted, and remaining in the <hi>Body;</hi> at ſome time or other <hi>(tandem aliquando)</hi> ſhould produce <hi>malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> Affects: from ſuch an occaſion ſometimes <hi>Leprous</hi> Maladies do appear.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He owns <hi>Purgatives</hi> to be <hi>virulent;</hi> which virulency, if it comes not out, but lodgeth in the Body, it produceth miſchief: And I cannot ſee how it ſhould be otherwiſe: For if it be true as this <hi>Author</hi> affirms; that ſome part of the Medicine is carried by the <hi>Bloud</hi> all over the Body; it is not like to come out again preſently; not that Day of Operation; The <hi>Venom</hi> then lies a breeding; and will bring forth in time. So that, when you <hi>Purge;</hi> you muſt take another to fetch out the <hi>virulency</hi> of the former: But if the <hi>ſecond</hi> be no better than the <hi>firſt;</hi> you muſt then take a <hi>third</hi> Doſe: And ſo you may <hi>Purge</hi> all the <hi>Year</hi> long at that rate of Purging, and be never the better, but much worſe hereafter.</p>
               <p>After this manner, there will be no end of <hi>Purging;</hi> but there may be an end of the <hi>Patient.</hi> If it be ſo, and I think it is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49195:8"/>ſo; Then ſuch pretended <hi>Purgations,</hi> is but <hi>Tinkerly Doings-Phyſitians</hi> and <hi>Pothecaries</hi> are very honeſt Men; but <hi>Phyſick</hi> cheats all the World.</p>
               <p>It is plain from the Words of the foregoing Author; what O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion he had of the common reputed <hi>Purgatives:</hi> Yet being ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to uſe them, for want of better, and more ſafe; he alſo did comply, with what his Judgment had condemned: As his <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Exemplars following do declare; and alſo his Preſcripts in Practice upon ſeveral Diſeaſes, in his Works extant.</p>
               <p>And other Men of repute in this <hi>Faculty,</hi> are of the ſame Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent in this matter; and have acknowledged as much: But for <hi>(à Salvo Judicio)</hi> to excuſe themſelves from perſiſting in known Errour; and to render the common <hi>Purgatives</hi> tolerably uſeful; until wholſomer, and ſafer be found out: They tell you of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectives,</hi> invented to ſubdue the <hi>Venom;</hi> to curb and tame the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant moleſting <hi>Qualities</hi> of the <hi>Purgatives;</hi> that they ſhall perform the Office of <hi>Purging,</hi> and not diſguſt or moleſt you in the Operation.</p>
               <p>True, part of this may be; and the <hi>Purgatives</hi> ſtill what they ought not to be. Perhaps the <hi>Patient</hi> does not find preſent Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience or Diſturbance: But that does not prove the <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Wholſomneſs</hi> of the corrected <hi>Purgatives;</hi> and yet moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly it is otherwiſe, and the Operation unpleaſant. Injurious and <hi>unwholſom</hi> Diet does not ſhew its ill effects preſently: You eat and drink with Pleaſure, and perceive no <hi>Hurt;</hi> but you will find it afterwards; perhaps a good while after: And ſo it is with bad Medicines, ſuch as ſtand in need of <hi>Correctives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Queſtion</hi> ariſeth; whether the <hi>Correction</hi> given to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent <hi>Purgatives,</hi> be due <hi>Correction,</hi> or only a <hi>Palliation?</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your <hi>Correction</hi> does raſe out, and extinguiſh the <hi>Venom;</hi> as to make the <hi>Concrete</hi> purely innocent and wholſom? I believe not ſo.</p>
               <p>You may poſſibly correct, or ſmother ſome extravagant <hi>Quality</hi> more eminent, and apparently noxious to Human Bodies; but you do not change the whole <hi>Nature</hi> thereof, which is <hi>Malign</hi> and <hi>Hoſtile.</hi> If you correct the ſmell of a <hi>T</hi>— with Musk and Civet; that the offenſive ſcent thereof is not perceived; yet it is a <hi>T</hi>— ſtill; an impure Excrement.</p>
               <p>So you may correct ſome of the <hi>firſt,</hi> or <hi>ſecond Qualities</hi> of the Purgatives, that are not ſufferable in the Operation: But being malign <hi>(tota ſubſtantia)</hi> in their whole Nature; the <hi>Correctives</hi> are not ſufficient ſecurity to ſave harmleſs, from future Damage.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49195:9"/>You may allay, and blunt the edge of ſome fierce <hi>Punging,</hi> or <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinating</hi> Property, and make the Operation more <hi>placid,</hi> and <hi>pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs;</hi> but there may be other injurious Qualities, which are <hi>dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> at preſent; and may produce ill effects, ſome <hi>Weeks,</hi> or <hi>Months</hi> after. If you knock out one <hi>Tooth;</hi> there are more left that will bite, and do hurt.</p>
               <p>After this manner you may eat a <hi>Toad,</hi> and have a correcting <hi>Antidote,</hi> that it ſhall not poyſon you. But I don't like ſuch <hi>Food,</hi> that wants ſo much <hi>Correction;</hi> Nor ſuch <hi>Phyſick:</hi> For when you think all the danger is paſt; there may be miſchief breeding. So that you cannot ſay you are <hi>ſecure;</hi> though at preſent you are ſeemingly well.</p>
               <p>Some that are dextrous in <hi>Poyſoning;</hi> can give that which does not ſoon diſcover its <hi>venomous</hi> Nature to hurt you: But after ſome <hi>Time,</hi> it will operate upon you ſenſibly, and by <hi>Degrees;</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>tabefie</hi> the Body, and ſo infeſt the <hi>Life;</hi> that you ſhall <hi>dwindle</hi> away, and know not what was the cauſe.</p>
               <p>Some <hi>Poyſons</hi> are Mortal, and kill preſently: others not ſo Mortal, but very hurtful; acting ſlowly and gradually: Diſguiſed under the Name of ſome common <hi>Diſeaſe;</hi> producing different effects. Some cauſe <hi>Dulneſs, Melancholly,</hi> and <hi>Stupidity:</hi> others provoke <hi>Laughter, Lust,</hi> or <hi>Fury:</hi> and ſome cauſe <hi>Convulsions, Dyſenteries, Inflammations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Some <hi>Poyſons</hi> more peculiarly and immediately affect the <hi>Heart;</hi> others ſeize the <hi>Brain;</hi> ſome invade the <hi>Liver;</hi> others the <hi>Lungs:</hi> ſome hurt the <hi>Bladder,</hi> as <hi>Cantharides:</hi> others dart their Venom chiefly upon the <hi>Genitals,</hi> and diſable either <hi>Sex,</hi> cauſing <hi>Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> All which is confirmed by Authors of Repute.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not point at the Parts of the Body, particularly this or that <hi>Purgative,</hi> ſhall more eſpecially injure: But we may conclude it will fall <hi>ſomewhere;</hi> and you muſt take it for your Pains, as it falls out</p>
               <p>Your Correction ſometimes is before <hi>Compoſition;</hi> and then you do ſomething to <hi>meliorate,</hi> at leaſt <hi>mitigate:</hi> yet, after you have done all you can; 'tis but <hi>(minus malum)</hi> not ſo bad as it was; and that's the beſt that can be ſaid. But who is the Superviſing <hi>Corrector,</hi> in theſe weighty Matters; that require much Care, and Skill? The Doctor he referrs all, and truſts the <hi>Apothecary;</hi> the <hi>Apothecary</hi> truſts the <hi>Boys:</hi> Then the <hi>Patient</hi> he muſt Truſt in <hi>God;</hi> for there is no Truſt in Man.</p>
               <p>He that <hi>Purgeth</hi> with Medicine, that requires ſo much <hi>Correction,</hi> and is not <hi>Operator</hi> himſelf; He alſo deſerves <hi>Correcting</hi> Reproof.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49195:9"/>
               <p>But more often, the <hi>Correctives</hi> are added in compoſition: And ſuch are not properly ſo called; but are only <hi>Palliatives:</hi> For, being thruſt into the Croud of Ingredients, they do not expunge or raſe out the <hi>Venom</hi> of <hi>Purgatives;</hi> but only enable Nature to bear the <hi>Aſſaults;</hi> to reſiſt and expel downwards, for to free her ſelf by Evacuation. And ſuch palliating <hi>Correctives</hi> are the <hi>Aromatics</hi> and <hi>Cardiacs;</hi> that are aſſociated with the <hi>malign</hi> Purgatives; that the <hi>Patient</hi> ſhall not be ſo <hi>ſenſible</hi> of the <hi>miſchievous</hi> Properties of the Medicine in the Operation; and for a quick and expeditious Expulſion.</p>
               <p>By this ſame Art of <hi>Sophistication;</hi> an ingenious <hi>Cook</hi> will prepare you a Meſs of <hi>Pottage,</hi> made with tainted <hi>unwholeſom</hi> Fleſh; corrected with a high Seaſon of well-ſavour'd Herbs, Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Spices, and ſuch-like Correctives. The <hi>Broth</hi> may be pleaſing enough to the <hi>Palate,</hi> and nothing ill diſcernable: But you may judge they cannot produce <hi>wholeſom</hi> Nouriſhment. And ſo adulterate <hi>Wines</hi> are made palatable and pleaſant in the drinking; but the ill Effects come after. And thus it is, with <hi>virulent</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Medicines.</p>
               <p>I think it unreaſonable, that the Work of Purgation, which is cleanſing and purifying; ſhould be intended and attempted to be <hi>wrought,</hi> by ſuch means as <hi>ſtain, vitiate,</hi> and <hi>defile</hi> the Body; if not expelled and caſt out. And all this hath ariſed from a <hi>Miſtake;</hi> ſuppoſing every thing that cauſeth <hi>Evacuation,</hi> does perform the Office of <hi>Purgation:</hi> But that's a grand Error; which hath intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſo many <hi>virulent</hi> Productions of Nature (deſigned for other Uſes) to be reputed and eſtabliſhed, in the <hi>Claſſes</hi> of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Works extant of our Predeceſſors; that have been Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians to <hi>Emperors, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> I find their Practice hath been managed by ſuch injurious <hi>Purgatives,</hi> (very likely it is ſo now:) And we may reaſonably conclude; that thoſe <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> Men of the World; had their <hi>Share,</hi> and their <hi>Fate;</hi> in ſuch miſchievous <hi>Drugs:</hi> For, had their <hi>Phyſicians</hi> known better; they would have been more benign to Mankind, than to have concealed them; and recommend that which is worſe to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Uſe.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Topping</hi> Men of <hi>Government</hi> he ſo ſerved; How are their <hi>Fleets,</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> provided for? Bad enough I know; and too bad. The <hi>Soldiers,</hi> and the <hi>Sea-men,</hi> they have <hi>Phyſick,</hi> ſuch as it is; and that muſt ſerve. But how can it be otherwiſe? ſince
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49195:10"/>the Inſpection, and Care is committed to them, that know no better: And therefore all is approved very well.</p>
               <p>I do aſſert; and not without good Reaſon and Experience; that Curing may be managed, without <hi>virulent</hi> Purgatives, or <hi>loathſom naſty</hi> Phyſick; and that much more pleaſing to <hi>Patients,</hi> and more hopeful in Effect: But <hi>Dogs</hi>-Tird, <hi>Horſe</hi>-Dung, <hi>Piſs,</hi> and many ſuch ſordid Inventions; I don't like, nor uſe: But they that know no better, muſt make uſe of ſuch. Becauſe ſome in their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity have been conſtrained to uſe ſuch, for Help in their Extremity, (not knowing what was more wholeſom and pleaſing to Nature) and caſual Succeſs hath hapned thereupon: This is ſet down in <hi>Receipt</hi>-Books, and noted for <hi>specific</hi> Remedies in ſuch Caſes; as if nothing elſe could do it; at leaſt, nothing ſo well. As if there were not Phyſick ſufficient in the <hi>wholeſom</hi> Stores of Nature, to perform all neceſſary <hi>Operations</hi> in Curing; but we muſt ſeek a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Venoms,</hi> and <hi>Excrements</hi> of <hi>Animals,</hi> to fetch it from thence, for internal Medicine; tho' unwholeſom, or loathſom and diſguſtful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly;</hi> From the <hi>Cenſure, Cautions,</hi> and <hi>Corrections</hi> of the evil Qualities, of reputed Purgatives; by Phyſicians of Note, that have uſed them in former Ages; and alſo by ſuch, as do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the uſe of them at this Time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scammony</hi> is a Purgative moſt frequently uſed; and is in moſt of the <hi>purging</hi> Medicines, both <hi>Electuaries</hi> and <hi>Pills</hi> of the Shops. The Ancients, and among them <hi>Aegineta</hi> and <hi>Meſue;</hi> ſets down Five great Faults in <hi>Scammony,</hi> which <hi>Fritagius</hi> rehearſeth, and concludes; <q>Scammonium nunquam eſſe exhibendum, quin ſit Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum; niſi Animas negotiari, &amp; Christianam charitatem abjicere decretum ſit. <bibl>Auror. Med. lib. 2. cap. 13.</bibl>
                  </q> And therefore great Cautions, and Inventions are uſed, to correct the <hi>virulent</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign</hi> Qualities of this Drug: And about theſe <hi>Corrections,</hi> there are different <hi>Opinions</hi> among <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> how rightly and beſt to be done; which I forbear to recite.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turbith,</hi> another Purgative much uſed; hath its Faults too: <hi>Tres ineſſe noxas in Turpetho ferunt ſapientes,</hi> ſays <hi>Fritagius.</hi> Which I forbear to ſet down for brevity ſake. And that this hath had a bad Name in the World, the old Verſe doth witneſs: <q>Nolo damnoſum Turbith, mea Viſcera turbet.</q>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49195:10"/>And becauſe it nauſeates and offends the <hi>Stomach;</hi> ſome will have the Word <hi>Turbith,</hi> derived <hi>à turbando;</hi> ſays <hi>Fallopius.</hi> But cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectves muſt help all theſe Faults: And therefore it is put into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Shop-Compoſitions; as a good Ingredient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Coloquintida</hi> is a Purgative very often uſed; an Ingredient in many of the common purging Medicines. The virulence and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence thereof is noted by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny Authors. <hi>Fallopius</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Eſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camentum periculoſum, niſi maxima adhibeatur cuſtodia.</hi> And <hi>Solenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> in the the laſt of his Counſels, calls <hi>Coloquintida (Poma Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli)</hi> the Devil's Apples. <hi>Meſue</hi> gives it the Name of <hi>fel terrae, &amp; mors Plantarum:</hi> Becauſe it kills the Plants that grow near it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Freitagius</hi> reckons up the evil Qualities of this Drug. <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatione conſtat, ventriculo, jecori, &amp; cordi admodum nocere; hoc malignitate ſua oppugnare, omniaque viſcera mirifice diſturbare; Stomachum valde concutere, ejuſque &amp; Inteſtinorum parietes vellicare, arrodere &amp; eradere; vaſorum &amp; vinarum oſcula reſerare,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 336. Since it is manifeſtly ſo; then they conſult how to maſter this Devil, that he ſhall not do ſo much miſchief: Some will fetter him after this manner; others think it more ſecure, another way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scammony, Turbith,</hi> and <hi>Coloquintida;</hi> theſe three famous Drugs are in uſe: Being in divers Compoſitions of the Shop-Medicines; both in the <hi>Electuaries,</hi> and <hi>Pills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As <hi>Benedicta Laxativa; Diacharthamum; de Citro ſolutivum; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio Hamech; Hiera Logadii,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pilulae Aggregativae; Pil.Cochiae; Pil. Foetidae; Pil. de lapide Lazuli; Pil. ex Duobue; Pil. Rudii,</hi> where is more of Art: But after all the Labour by <hi>Trituration, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi> and <hi>Diſtillation,</hi> it is but a rude Medicine; not a true Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaive. Who can bring a clean thing, out of an unclean? <hi>Nil dat, quod non habet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Inventions ſurpaſs my Underſtanding, and every one elſe; to give a rational Account of the Deſigns thereof.</p>
               <p>There is much to be ſaid upon the Examination of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions (if it were my Buſineſs now) and I could allow Time to enquire into the Reaſons of their ſeveral Aſſociations of Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients; and to note their incongruous and ſuperfluous Additions: Which proceed from <hi>Imbecillity</hi> of Judgment, to compoſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular true Medicine; or elſe deſigned to amuſe the World, in compounding and confounding Ingredients, good and bad together diſcordantly.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49195:11"/>
               <p>Such farraginous Mixtures cauſed <hi>Helmont</hi>'s Diſlike and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint: <q>Commiſeror in Officinis tot Simplicium connexiones, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſas miſcellaneas, proditrices ignorantiae &amp; incertitudinis: sperant enim Scholae, Si non juvet unum, alterum juvaturum: ſicque multa aſſociant invicem. <bibl>Van Helm. Pharmacopolium.</bibl>
                  </q> And in the ſame Page, theſe Words do follow: <q>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiquaque enim pro ſuo Nummo decipitur Aeger; tam ſcilieet fide ac fraude Seplaſiae, quam jureju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando Doctoratus.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſula</hi> is the <hi>genus</hi> of <hi>Tithymals,</hi> compriſing under that Name ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts: Bad is the beſt. <hi>Eſula minor</hi> is accounted the ſafeſt, and moſt in uſe; ſuppoſed to purge watery Humors: But it muſt be corrected; elſe it will do great hurt. <hi>Quod Cordi, Epati, Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triculo, Viſceribuſque noxia vim alioquin inferret maximum; Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina raderet, nobiles interiorum partes inflammaret, Venarum ora reſeraret, Febres excitaret, Sperma exſiccando conſumeret, poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiamque Aphrodiſiam extingueret.</hi> Freitag. <hi>pag.</hi> 414. A foul Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this noble Purger: One of the Ingredients of theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. <hi>Pilulae Mechoacanae; Pil. Foetidae;</hi> and <hi>Electuar. Benedict. Laxativa;</hi> that bleſſed Electuary: (A fair Title to a foul Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.) But how oft it comes into the Recipes, I cannot ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euphorbium,</hi> a condenſate Juice; ſuppoſed to purge <hi>Phlegm,</hi> and <hi>watery</hi> Humors; is commended and uſed againſt <hi>Apoplexies, Palſies, ſoporiferous</hi> Diſeaſes, <hi>Convulſions, Tremors, Dropſies,</hi> and <hi>Gout.</hi> Theſe are great Diſeaſes; and therefore it was thought, they muſt have Medicines extraordinary, (but let them be extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary good then) not extraordinary dangerous, as this <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbium</hi> is; more likely to make a Diſeaſe than to cure one: And therefore it is cautiouſly to be dealt with, and ſo adviſed. <q>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspectè per omnia ejus uſus eſt ineundus; quod Fauces inflammet, interiora vellicet, urat &amp; arrodat, Stomachum &amp; Epar mirificè la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſat; adeò ut ſudorem frigidum, ſummam Cordis anguſtiam, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſyncopen concitet, &amp;c. <bibl>Freitag. auror. Med. <hi>pag.</hi> 341.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now you ſee what a hopeful Account is given of this <hi>Purgative,</hi> But for a Mitigation, and to bridle the Fury of this Drug; there are ſeveral ways propoſed for Correction, according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgments of Phyſicians. <hi>Meſue, Avicen, Serapio, Manar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, Quercetan,</hi> and others. But I intend never to uſe it inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally; and therefore ſhall not examine the Corrections, which is beſt: For I think it beſt not to meddle with it internally. But it may be uſed outwardly in <hi>Epipaſtic</hi> Plaſters, to raiſe Bliſters; as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49195:11"/>it is ſo uſed ſometimes. But I find it an Ingredient in <hi>Pil. Foetidae;</hi> and <hi>de Hermodactilis:</hi> Probably it comes ſometimes into the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes;</hi> for I meet with a Correction of it in the <hi>Pharmacopoeia Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinenſis;</hi> and for external Application, there needs no Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>I might proceed on, and go through the whole Catalogue of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Purgatives; after this manner to ſhew their <hi>Virulency;</hi> or Inſufficiency to perform the Work of <hi>Purgation,</hi> by ſuch ill <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> they are pregnant with: But that would be tedious to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all of them, ſingly by their Names, and recite the Cenſure that is given of them, by Phyſicians that have uſed them: I ſhall therefore give the Character of them in the groſs; according to the Sentiment of ſome Authors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Van Helmont</hi> giving Judgment upon Medicines, hath theſe Words: <q>Laxativa peculiariter ſenſi operari duntaxat, propter la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens intus ſibi venenum.</q>
That the common <hi>Purgatives</hi> operate as <hi>Venoms.</hi> And ſoon after he adds:
<q>Senſi ideò Laxativa putrefacere vitales Succos.</q> That they putrefie the vital Liquors. <hi>Poteſtas Medicaminum,</hi> pag. 383.</p>
               <p>And another <hi>Author,</hi> whoſe Writings are well known, and eſteemed in this Kingdom and abroad, ſaith: <q>Porro alia Cathar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica, uti Jalapium, Colocynthis, Elaterium, &amp; quaedam Mercurii praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratu, particulis acrioribus &amp; non raro ſepticis conſtant; quae propterea ab Inteſtinis ſuſcepta, indeque ſanguini tranſmiſſa, Maſſam ejus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigniter fundunt, &amp; in ſeroſitatem valde praecipitant; imo interdum quaſi venenant, &amp; Craſin ejus corumpunt. <bibl>Dr. <hi>Willis de Purg.</hi> pag. 71.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This is muchwhat to the ſame purpoſe, as the foregoing <hi>Author</hi> determined of <hi>Purgatives.</hi> And a little after (<hi>pag.</hi> 72.) relating how two Children were killed with a <hi>Mercurial</hi> Pouder, by an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyrick</hi> at <hi>Oxford:</hi> 
                  <q>Nec tantum à mercurialibus, ſed ab aliis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Catharticis, è vegetabilium familia de ſumptis, Maſſa ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea it a depravatur, ut non niſi longo tempore reſtitui aut renovari poſſit.</q> Not only mercurial, but <hi>vegetable</hi> Purgatives, ſometimes do ſo deprave the Maſs of Blood; that it will be a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can be reſtored. Dr. <hi>Willis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he confirms what <hi>Helmont</hi> had ſaid of the common <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> in theſe Words: <q>Adeo non immeritò prorſus Calumniatur Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montius dicens Pharmaca Cathartica non ſemper, aut ſolummodo humores in corpore prius exiſtentes educere; ſed potentiâ ſua cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptiva, depravatos efficere. <bibl>Idem, ibidem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49195:12"/>
               <p>Now what do you think of the common <hi>Purges;</hi> made with half a <hi>douzen,</hi> or half a <hi>ſcore,</hi> of ſuch Ingredients as have been diſcourſed on? <hi>Magis à Remedio, quam ab ipſo Morbo timendum ſit.</hi> If you like'em, much good may do you; but I do not, and never ſhall; becauſe I know better things.</p>
               <p>You may ſee now, (if you have Eyes and Underſtanding) what Effects are to be expected from ſuch <hi>Purgatives;</hi> how apt they are to deprave, inſtead of purifying the vital <hi>Juices,</hi> for reducing an ill habit of Body to a ſound ſtate: And 'tis the Judgment of the <hi>Learned;</hi> but they have a learned way of <hi>Correction;</hi> that they ſhall not do ſo much Hurt, as otherwiſe they would.</p>
               <p>There is another Help found out; and that is the cauſe why Phyſicians ſend ſo many to the <hi>Waters:</hi> To rinſe out, and fetch off the <hi>Stains,</hi> and <hi>virulent Impreſſions</hi> of <hi>counterfeit Purgatives.</hi> I ſhould like the <hi>Waters</hi> well enough; if they would operate, and perform the Intention in a leſſer Quantity: But to pour down <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three Quarts</hi> in a Forenoon; to charge and chill the Body with ſo much; tho' ſome do bear it pretty well; yet others receive Prejudice, inſtead of a Benefit. He that is Maſter of a wholeſom Purgative, will do better Service, than all the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Purgative,</hi> is a promiſing good Name; which invites, and makes the pretended <hi>Purgatives</hi> go down the better. They are ſuch as the World hath been uſed to; and the People take them; becauſe others have taken them before: They know no better, and therefore theſe are the beſt, and they muſt try their <hi>Fate</hi> with them. They are ſuch as <hi>Tradition</hi> hath handed down from Age to Age; to the preſent Time; and Cuſtom hath made them familiar: They are recommended (ſometimes diſcomended) and appointed by the <hi>Learned</hi> in <hi>vogue;</hi> and therefore they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and readily received, as if they were ſent by <hi>Divine</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, to heal the Infirmities of human frail Nature.</p>
               <p>But all this is, no convincing Argument; to prove their ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and fitneſs, for the important Work of <hi>Purgation;</hi> Errour is as old as Time it ſelf; but ſuch falſe <hi>Substitutes,</hi> will wear out of <hi>Date,</hi> and out of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> when better ſhall appear manifeſtly and convincingly; as by comparing theſe pretended and fallacious; with what is purifying and truly purgative, as followeth.</p>
               <p>Having ſhewed <hi>negatively,</hi> what true <hi>Purgatives</hi> are not; by examining and ſetting forth the malign Nature of common repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Purgatives: In their <hi>Operations;</hi> in their <hi>Corrections;</hi> by their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49195:12"/>
                  <hi>Effects;</hi> by the <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Cenſure,</hi> of Ancient and Modern Phyſicians.</p>
               <p>I come now to aſſert <hi>poſitively;</hi> and ſet down the <hi>Qualifications</hi> of a true <hi>Purgative</hi> Medicine; that performs the Office of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> according to the Intent, and Meaning of that Operation, in due Manner, and alſo in Effects.</p>
               <p>A Medicine adapted truly <hi>Purgative,</hi> is endowed with theſe <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> and <hi>excellent</hi> Properties.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Balſamic, wholeſom</hi> and <hi>harmleſs</hi> in all the Ingredients.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Fermentative,</hi> to ſeparate and depurate; wherein is compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Aperitive</hi> and <hi>Abſterſive</hi> Faculties.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Lenitive</hi> and <hi>Placid</hi> in Operation.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Catholic</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſive;</hi> as adapt and applicable to all Caſes, requiring <hi>Purgative</hi> Energy</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt:</hi> A true <hi>Purgative</hi> wants no <hi>Correction,</hi> as being <hi>whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom,</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> in all the Parts of Compoſition: That's a Medicine amicable and pleaſing to Nature. And if <hi>no good</hi> can be done, (as in Caſes <hi>irremediable,</hi> and paſt hope) it will do <hi>no hurt;</hi> but give you the Satisfaction of a Tryal. And in Diſeaſes <hi>obſtinate,</hi> and <hi>difficult</hi> to be removed; requiring a <hi>Method,</hi> and Medicines of a different Operation to be aſſiſtant; then the <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi> performs only a Part; but neceſſarily conducing to the <hi>Cure;</hi> and without this probably no perfect <hi>Cure.</hi> But where there is a capacity to receive Relief; you may be bold in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated uſe thereof, for obtaining the deſired Effect.</p>
               <p>But if it wants this <hi>wholeſom</hi> Qualification, it cannot be a true <hi>purifying</hi> Purgative: And that Defect, makes a great Abatement in Virtue; or Fruſtration of the Intention.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly:</hi> A true <hi>Purgative</hi> acts by a benign and placid <hi>fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative</hi> Operation; which is diffuſive through the Body; opening and ſearching into all Parts; ſeparating that which is <hi>bad,</hi> to be brought down, and ſent away by the <hi>Inteſtines;</hi> leaving that which is <hi>good,</hi> to ſupport and maintain the Body: Does not contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, nor drain out the <hi>alimentary</hi> Juices; from whence Allevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion does follow, and natural Strength preſerved.</p>
               <p>And every <hi>Evacuation,</hi> that is not performed after this manner; cannot rightly be called <hi>Purgation;</hi> nor in Reaſon can you expect the good Effects otherwiſe: For, true <hi>Purgation</hi> is not a <hi>promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49195:13"/>Evacuation; an emptying of the <hi>Guts</hi> only; of a draining of the Body by force, without diſtinction of Matter: But <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating</hi> all uſeleſs, ſuperfluous, and degenerate <hi>Humors;</hi> that the <hi>vital</hi> Liquors may be preſerved pure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly:</hi> A true <hi>Purging</hi> Medicine, operates <hi>gradually</hi> and <hi>gently;</hi> takes Time to ſearch out, and fetch out the <hi>morbific</hi> Matter. Moderate and gentle Evacuation, is one ſign of a true <hi>Purgative:</hi> But you do not deſerve a good Medicine; if you will not allow Time ſufficient for the Operation.</p>
               <p>A good <hi>wholeſom</hi> Medicine is working <hi>ſecretly</hi> within the Body, all the Intervals of Evacuation; collecting impure Matter toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of divers Parts; and in due time ſends it forth calmly without diſturbance: For if it do not work <hi>moderately</hi> and <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately,</hi> it cannot perform the Office of <hi>true Purgation:</hi> This is an Operation of <hi>Time,</hi> and no hurrying Buſineſs.</p>
               <p>Many People are for a <hi>Purge</hi> that works quick and often; and are very impatient if it operates <hi>little,</hi> and <hi>ſlowly:</hi> They muſt have a <hi>galloping</hi> Purge; one of the <hi>virulent</hi> and <hi>worſer</hi> ſort; ſuch they like <hi>beſt.</hi> It is not the many <hi>Stools,</hi> that makes <hi>Purging</hi> ſo advantageous in Curing; but Matter <hi>offending</hi> collected in a <hi>few</hi> Stools; is that which makes <hi>Evacuation</hi> helpful and ſucceſsful.</p>
               <p>If you ſpurr <hi>Nature,</hi> with a ſtimulating <hi>venemous</hi> Purgative, out of her own gentle <hi>Pace;</hi> you muſt not expect <hi>Purgation</hi> (which is <hi>Purification</hi>) from ſuch <hi>rough, rude, haſty</hi> Proceedings: You have then but a <hi>promiſcuous</hi> Evacuation; <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> together; and that may be more injurious, than beneficial.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Placid</hi> and <hi>Moderate</hi> Evacuation, proceeds from <hi>wholeſom</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives: But when they are <hi>venemous,</hi> and <hi>diſguſtful;</hi> Nature can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer them to abide long in the Body; but labours vigorouſly to expel in great haſte: And that's one ſign of a bad Medicine; not a <hi>true Purgative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly:</hi> A true <hi>Purgative</hi> Medicine, ſo qualified as before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated; is alſo <hi>Catholic</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſive,</hi> in the <hi>Claſſis</hi> of <hi>Purgation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Purgation is a <hi>Catholic</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſive</hi> Operation; required and uſeful in all <hi>Caſes,</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes:</hi> Either <hi>ſingly,</hi> and to perform alone; or is premitted, and leads foremoſt in a <hi>Method:</hi> Or is uſed <hi>intermittingly</hi> in the Courſe; or elſe comes in at the latter end, to carry off the <hi>Relicts</hi> of a Diſeaſe; and is <hi>ſo</hi> uſed as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in the moſt malignant Caſes, <hi>Small Pox</hi> and <hi>Peſtilential Fevers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Purgation</hi> be ſo efficacious and extenſive; as requiſite in all Diſeaſes; then a <hi>Purgative</hi> and <hi>Depurative</hi> Medicine, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49195:13"/>forms this Office well and truly; deſerves the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Catholic,</hi> for being ſerviceable and uſeful in all Caſes. But although <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may be granted ſuch a Latidude of <hi>Operation:</hi> yet <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> of a ſingle Medicine, few there are, can allow of <hi>that;</hi> and are more ready to deride, than approve of ſuch an Expedient; for the <hi>Learned</hi> in <hi>Phyſick</hi> never taught them ſo: And they ſay, there is no ſuch thing in Nature.</p>
               <p>This is not the <hi>first</hi> time, the <hi>Learned</hi> have been miſtaken: I am not guided by all what they ſay; but ſometimes by my own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> herein: And therefore I do aſſert, (againſt any <hi>traditional, falſe-bottom'd</hi> Learning) That a true <hi>Purgative,</hi> and <hi>Purifying</hi> Medicine; performs that Office in all <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Caſes.</hi> But this is againſt the Phyſicians <hi>Intereſt;</hi> and therefore they will not have it ſo; that the Deſign of <hi>Adaptation</hi> to different <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> might paſs unqueſtioned. I have much to ſay upon this <hi>Intrigue,</hi> if I would ravel into it, and examine the <hi>Politicks</hi> thereof: But let it paſs.</p>
               <p>This Practice, of appropriating <hi>Purges</hi> to <hi>Conſtitutions;</hi> was rational enough, and then neceſſary; when <hi>Purgatives</hi> were ſuppoſed to operate <hi>(electivè)</hi> by attracting peculiarly this, or that different <hi>Humor,</hi> luxuriant and infeſting ſeveral Bodies: But now the Caſe is alter'd; and <hi>Purgatives</hi> are acknowledged to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>(fermentativè)</hi> by <hi>Fermentation;</hi> thereby to ſeparate and caſt off any <hi>Humor</hi> abounding, or degenerate Matter.</p>
               <p>True <hi>Purgative</hi> Fermentation, does not reſpect and level at this, or that particular <hi>Humor;</hi> but ſeparates all ſuperfluous and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate <hi>Matter;</hi> makes it ready for <hi>Protruſion,</hi> and <hi>Excluſion. Quali quiſquis Humore abundaverit; talis evacuatur.</hi> Now <hi>elective</hi> Purgation is out of Doors; <hi>fermentative</hi> Purification comes in; as a more generous, general, and comprehenſive <hi>Operation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I meet with an <hi>Author</hi> concurring herein, and aſſerting muchwhat to this purpoſe. <hi>Nec quidem Philoſophum, aut quempiam <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; ratione utentem decet aſſerere, Pharmaca ulla propter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae ſimilitudinem, aut virtutes neſcio quas specificas, in deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum quemvis humorem agere, cumque ſineerum &amp; peculiarem foras educere.</hi> Dr. <hi>Willis de Purg.</hi> p. 70.</p>
               <p>Although this <hi>Author</hi> did not intend by thoſe Words, to prove what I now drive at; yet they are uſeful for my Purpoſe, and confirming what I have aſſerted; touching <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> of a <hi>ſingle</hi> Medicine in <hi>Purgative</hi> Operation: For, if no <hi>Purging</hi> Medicine acts peculiarly upon; or ſelects and draws out any <hi>Humor</hi> from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49195:14"/>the reſt; but only raiſeth a <hi>Fermentation,</hi> and excites Nature thereby to ſeparate, depurate, and exclude what is peccant and diſturbing: Then that Medicine which doth procure, ſuch a <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> benignly and placidly; performs the Work of <hi>Purgation,</hi> to all Intents and Purpoſes, in divers Perſons, and various Caſes.</p>
               <p>From hence you may underſtand; there is no neceſſity of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Purgative</hi> Medicines to <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> and different Diſeaſes; but that a true <hi>Purgative</hi> is <hi>Catholic,</hi> and advantagiouſly uſeful in all Caſes whatever, requiring ſuch an <hi>Operation:</hi> Yet I do allow that ſuch a general <hi>Medicine,</hi> of that Latitude and Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; may be <hi>specificated,</hi> as pointing and aiming at, more directly and ſpecially.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>When;</hi> how <hi>oft;</hi> and in what <hi>Caſes,</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative <hi>Operation</hi> ought to be uſed.</head>
               <p>There are two principal Occaſions requiring <hi>Purgation:</hi> One is <hi>Preſervative,</hi> or <hi>Preventive;</hi> the other <hi>Curative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Preſervation from <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> is very requiſite: As when any <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> finds ſome unwonted Alteration, or Indiſpoſition; 'tis a good <hi>Time</hi> then, to uſe preventing means: For, it is much better, and ſafer to prevent <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> than to delay until it ſeize you. <hi>Aegriùs ejicitur, quam non admittitur hoſtis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All that we receive into the Body, is not fit to be retained; but <hi>Part</hi> of our <hi>Food,</hi> is tranſmuted, and aſſimilated as uſeful to maintain the Body: And <hi>Part</hi> is rejected, ſeparated, and caſt forth, as excrementitious and uſeleſs; by <hi>Stool,</hi> by <hi>urinary Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,</hi> by the <hi>Pores,</hi> and other <hi>Emunctories.</hi> When <hi>Nature</hi> keeps this courſe duly; and being able to perform this daily Work ſteadily and conſtantly; there will be no need of <hi>Purging:</hi> But from <hi>Intemperance;</hi> improper and injurious <hi>Food;</hi> vitious or evil <hi>Cuſtoms;</hi> Debility of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Caſualties:</hi> The <hi>Order,</hi> and due <hi>Execution</hi> of Bodily Functions is thereby ſubverted; from whence <hi>Relicts,</hi> or degenerate Matter, remains and infects ſeveral Parts of the <hi>Body;</hi> which ought timely to be evacuated and diſcharged; or elſe <hi>Sickneſs</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> will ariſe from thence variouſly; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Nature of the <hi>humoral</hi> Matter tainting the <hi>Blood,</hi> and Condition of the Part, where it infects, or affects; <hi>idiopathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> or <hi>ſympathically. Venienti occurrite Morbo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49195:14"/>
               <p>But moſt commonly this Caution, and Advice of Prevention, is put off, and neglected: The Proſecution of <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> or <hi>Profit;</hi> will not give Time for this neceſſary Work of preventive <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> But they ſuffer afterwards for their Folly. <hi>Sickneſs</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizeth; and then they are forced into <hi>Phyſick;</hi> but now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a great deal will not do; what a little might have done before.</p>
               <p>All Bodies contract a <hi>Foulneſs</hi> within; ſome more, ſome leſs: Some are ſtrong, and bear it out longer; others weaker of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and the ſooner fall into <hi>Sickneſs;</hi> or diſpoſed thereto by the different <hi>Formation,</hi> and natural Condition of <hi>Body:</hi> Therefore to <hi>purge</hi> and <hi>purifie</hi> with a wholeſome true Purgative Medicine; is the beſt Preventive to keep off <hi>Diſeaſes;</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Body</hi> ſound, in a healthful and vigorous ſtate. But if your Purges be of the common Sort, <hi>virulent</hi> and <hi>unwholeſom;</hi> that imitate and counterfeit the Office of <hi>Purging,</hi> but performs it not: I cannot ſay, they are true <hi>Preſervatives</hi> of <hi>Health;</hi> nor may you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the laudable Effects of <hi>purgative</hi> Operation, from ſuch feigned, deceitful Medicines.</p>
               <p>For <hi>prevention,</hi> moſt People commonly chuſe the <hi>Spring,</hi> or <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn,</hi> to <hi>purge</hi> and cleanſe their Bodies; and they do well, and wiſely therein: But if any Alteration ſhould come, in the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of thoſe Seaſons; you may ſafely <hi>purge</hi> with a true <hi>purifying</hi> Medicine, at any Time of the Year; and with more ſafety pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably than to forbear, and deferr it until <hi>Spring,</hi> or <hi>Fall:</hi> For, though your Indiſpoſition be but ſmall at firſt, and may paſs off; yet you know not what it may prove, and how it may encreaſe: But let it prove how it will; you commit no Errour, in taking a wholeſom cleanſer, be it <hi>Froſt,</hi> or <hi>Dog-Days;</hi> only order your ſelf, as thoſe different Times do require: In <hi>Winter</hi> a warm Room; in <hi>Summer</hi> be moderate in motion, that may not cauſe Sweat; and then <hi>purgative</hi> Operation, will be kindly and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, at any Time of the Year.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Caution</hi> that was given by the <hi>Ancients,</hi> to forbear <hi>purging</hi> in the <hi>Dog-Days;</hi> does not concern us in this <hi>Latitude</hi> we live in; much different from the <hi>Heat</hi> of that <hi>Climate</hi> where they lived, <hi>Canis non mordet in Anglia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Time of <hi>Day,</hi> moſt ſit for Purging Medicines to be given; he Founders of this Art, appointed the <hi>Morning,</hi> as moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient: And conſidering what rough ſort of <hi>Purges</hi> they gave, that would not lye long in the <hi>Body,</hi> but fall to working ſoon; that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49195:15"/>Time was moſt proper: But a <hi>Purgative,</hi> that lyes eight or ten Hours quiet, before it operates; the Morning is not convenient: Becauſe the Medicine will put you by the due Time for Sleep; and will be working, when you ſhould be at Reſt the Night follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And therefore the <hi>Hour</hi> of the <hi>Day</hi> is to be fixed, as beſt ſuting with the Nature of the Medicine.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Catholic</hi> Medicine I appoint to be taken at Night going to Bed; becauſe it hinders not, but rather procures quiet Sleep; being wholeſom and amicable to Nature, placid and gentle in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Operation: And makes no Evacuation, until next Morning; perhaps near Noon, with ſome coſtive Bodies. But if your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Purge</hi> be of the common <hi>virulent</hi> ſort; the ſooner it comes out, the better; for ſuch <hi>Purgatives</hi> ought not to lye in the <hi>Body</hi> all Night.</p>
               <p>Having ſhewed how proper and convenient <hi>Purging</hi> is, for <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> of Diſeaſes; making ſigns of their Approach by ſome Alteration or Indiſpoſition of Body: We are next to conſider, and determine of <hi>Purgation,</hi> how it may be advantagious, when <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> are apparently ſeated, and actually moleſting, or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And now you are to be directed by <hi>Indications,</hi> ſuggeſting and declaring when to Purge.</p>
               <p>Ill Humors <hi>indicate</hi> and prompt <hi>Purgation; (nemine contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente)</hi> ſo agreed of all ſides: And ſuch depraved ill <hi>Humors,</hi> by a general Conſent alſo; are adjudged the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of moſt <hi>Diſeaſes;</hi> and fomenting or aggravating all the reſt. But notwithſtanding; the Rules of <hi>Art</hi> offers <hi>Contraindications,</hi> to barr the uſe of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> at certain Times, and under ſome diſagreeing Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: So that Purgation comes in neceſſarily to all, as a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic</hi> and General Remedy, only with this difference; That the <hi>Times</hi> convenient, for that <hi>Operation</hi> in every Diſeaſe, may duly be diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>And here I ſhall not need to ſpeak particularly to every <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> by their Names; but will take them in the groſs; and conſider them in their Nature, by which they are allied to each other; as having their <hi>Riſe,</hi> and <hi>Dependance</hi> upon <hi>humoral</hi> Cauſes; and do therefore require <hi>Purgation.</hi> For, ſuch as have <hi>Affinity</hi> and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance in <hi>Cauſation;</hi> may have, and very fitly, the ſame Means for <hi>Curation:</hi> Since <hi>Purgatives</hi> do not attract <hi>(electivè)</hi> this or that <hi>Humor</hi> particularly; (as before proved) but by <hi>Fermentation,</hi> which operates generally and comprehenſively, by ſeparating all <hi>peccant</hi> Humors, in order for their excluſion.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49195:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Names</hi> of Diſeaſes are different and various from <hi>Parts</hi> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and <hi>Functions</hi> impeded; when humoral <hi>Cauſes</hi> are the ſame; and therefore the <hi>purgative</hi> Indication for Curing, will be the ſame alſo. <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> being thus akin, by their <hi>humoral</hi> Cauſes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating and continuing; their <hi>Cures</hi> will not lie ſo far aſunder; but may be yoaked together in their going off.</p>
               <p>The <hi>People</hi> chatter as they are taught (by thoſe who want teaching themſelves) and are wheedled into a Belief; that every <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> which hath a particular <hi>Name,</hi> muſt alſo have as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily requiring; peculiar and different <hi>Medicines</hi> from all the reſt: This <hi>Miſtake,</hi> or <hi>Deſign;</hi> hath filled the World, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the People, with <hi>Thouſands</hi> of ſuperfluous, dubious, and ſometimes dangerous Medicines. You are not therefore obliged to change your <hi>Medicines,</hi> that perform the general and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Operations, (<hi>Purgative</hi> or <hi>Sudorific</hi>) ſo oft as <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> change their <hi>Names,</hi> yet retain their <hi>humoral</hi> Nature; which antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Cauſe,</hi> fixing here or there; infeſting this, or that part of the <hi>Body,</hi> gives occaſion for a new <hi>Denomination,</hi> although ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the old perambulating peccant <hi>Matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I own that <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> may ſo differ, as to require a different <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod;</hi> but notwithſtanding they may have the ſame <hi>Medicines,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and fitly, though not in the ſame Order. <hi>Purgatives</hi> moſt commonly begins the <hi>Cure; Sudorifics</hi> follow, if requiſite to be uſed: But when <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> are <hi>malignant, peracute,</hi> and <hi>dangerous;</hi> then a <hi>Sudorific</hi> leads foremoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foulneſs</hi> of Body, and <hi>Obſtructions;</hi> are the two general <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> prompting and pointing at <hi>Purgation:</hi> And therefore if you look through the Practice of <hi>Phyſick;</hi> let the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> be in any <hi>Part</hi> of the Body; Purging is appointed moſt commonly, as one of the <hi>firſt</hi> and chiefeſt <hi>Remedies:</hi> And is oftner repeated, and more relied on, than any other <hi>Operation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ill <hi>Humors</hi> beget <hi>Obſtructions:</hi> Therefore abſterſe, and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate the depraved <hi>Humors</hi> by Purgation; then you open <hi>Obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> and purifie the <hi>Body</hi> with one Operation.</p>
               <p>Since degenerate <hi>humoral</hi> Matter, injurious and unſerviceable, is brought forth by <hi>purgative</hi> Fermentation; and moſt Diſeaſes <hi>ariſe</hi> from, and have their <hi>Dependance</hi> upon ſuch <hi>Cauſes</hi> (by Conſent and Judgment of the Learned.) Then it follows neceſſarily; that a <hi>Medicine</hi> performing that <hi>Operation,</hi> well and truly; is ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable and helpful in all thoſe <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> cauſed by ſuch degenerate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49195:16"/>
                  <hi>Humors,</hi> and depraved <hi>Matter;</hi> let the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> be called and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, by what <hi>Name</hi> ſoever.</p>
               <p>But here I would not be ſo underſtood; as if I laid the whole Streſs of Curing in all Caſes, upon <hi>Purgation;</hi> but to let you know the <hi>Efficacy,</hi> and <hi>Extenſive</hi> Power of this <hi>Operation;</hi> being ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably and duly uſed in all <hi>Diſeaſes;</hi> and that in the <hi>moſt</hi> Caſes, it is <hi>mostly,</hi> and advantagiouſly uſed, above any other <hi>Operation:</hi> Yet there is a Time to forbear, and fit Times when to proſecute with <hi>Purging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now we are to ſay ſomthing concerning <hi>Contraindications;</hi> that do forbid <hi>Purgation</hi> at ſome unfit Times; which require ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Operation to be then uſed more properly: And this is called <hi>Method;</hi> whereby different <hi>Operations</hi> may come in ſeaſonably and duly, not praepoſterouſly and interfering.</p>
               <p>The grand <hi>Queſtion</hi> herein to be determined, is this: Will the peccant Matter conveniently go downwards by <hi>Purgation;</hi> or muſt it be ſent away from all Parts by <hi>Tranſpiration?</hi> Diſeaſes that have Malignity; as <hi>Small Pox, Meaſles, Malignant</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilential Fevers;</hi> when the Life is ſeized, and oppreſſed with ſuch venemous, ſuffocating Matter: Then <hi>ſudorific</hi> Operation is the chiefeſt, and moſt ſecure Help to rely on; for that diſperſeth the infectious <hi>Miaſm,</hi> and throws off <hi>(per poros)</hi> on every ſide: And when <hi>Nature</hi> (the <hi>Life</hi>) is diſentangled, and hath prevailed by ſuch means; then a true <hi>purgative</hi> and <hi>purifying</hi> Medicine, comes ſeaſonably afterwards, to perform the reſt: And this is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to be well and ſufficiently performed; elſe the <hi>Dregs</hi> and <hi>Impurities</hi> remaining behind, will produce other <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of very ill Conſequence, as it hath often proved ſo to many; by neglect of ſufficient and true <hi>Purgation,</hi> which is Purification: But when they have taken, two or three <hi>Purges,</hi> of the contaminating repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Purgatives;</hi> they think all is then done, that ought to be; but that's a great Miſtake, which will appear ſo, by the ill Effects that follow, ſome time after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How oft <hi>Purgative</hi> Operation may be uſed: And how <hi>long</hi> to be continued.</head>
               <p>For Satisfaction to theſe Demands; we are to make theſe two Inquiries: <hi>Firſt,</hi> What Ability and Strength the <hi>Perſon</hi> is of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49195:16"/>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> What <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> the Complaining labours under, or is inclined to, and endeavours prevention thereof.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Patient</hi> be weak, and worn down by Sickneſs; then give Intermiſſion accordingly; a Day or two; and the <hi>Doſe</hi> leſs than for others; that Nature may be refreſhed by Reſpite; not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, but enabled to proceed in the Operation, until the Body be sufficiently cleanſed. Always ſuppoſing this to be done by a wholeſom <hi>purifying</hi> Medicine; not the common reputed <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> that prey upon, and deprave the Body: But People vainly think, every <hi>Evacuation</hi> to be <hi>Purgation;</hi> which is a great Miſtake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Purgation</hi> is to be continued until the Symptoms complained of, do ceaſe. <hi>(Si qualia oportet purgentur, &amp; facilè ferant.)</hi> So long as the <hi>Patient</hi> bears the <hi>Operation</hi> well; Nature alleviated and finds Benefit; continue on (with due intermiſſions) to evacuate the <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral</hi> Cauſe, until the Body be cleanſed and freed from the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bific</hi> Matter; that there be no Remainder to breed, and cauſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe. <hi>Quae enim à Morbis relinquuntur, recidivas facere conſueve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> Aphor.</p>
               <p>But many <hi>People,</hi> when they find themſelves ſomething eaſed, and the worſt is paſt; they deſiſt from proſecuting; and leave Relicts behind, that procures a Return of the <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe as bad. Thus to their Prejudice, the moſt leave off the <hi>purgative</hi> Operation too ſoon; before they have finiſhed the Work of <hi>Cleanſing</hi> and <hi>Purifying:</hi> Twice or thrice Purging, they think is ſufficient; and are then weary, and unwilling to do more.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of this Averſneſs is from hence; they have been uſed to the common <hi>virulent Purgatives,</hi> which are diſguſtful and irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; and therefore Nature hath Reluctance againſt them, and People take them for meer neceſſity, and with an Ill-will; accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all purging Medicines to be much what alike, and diſpleaſing to Nature; but that's a great Miſtake: For when they ſhall have the uſe of a true <hi>Purgative,</hi> that is wholeſom, and eaſily perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Operation; they will find ſo much difference then; that <hi>Purging</hi> will be no more offenſive, or troubleſom, than natural Stools.</p>
               <p>And then you can hardly err in repeating it too often, or proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting to long with that Operation: For true <hi>Purging,</hi> which is <hi>Purifying;</hi> does not debilitate, but roborate; and therefore Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is well-pleaſed therewith, and receives ſuch a Medicine freely; becauſe ſhe finds Relief thereby.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49195:17"/>
               <p>I have heard ſome ſay; they are afraid to <hi>Purge,</hi> becauſe they are too weak; and Purging will make them weaker; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is the Opinion of their <hi>Phyſician:</hi> But I ſay otherwiſe; that none but thoſe, who are incapable of Help, and not like to live, are unfit to <hi>Purge:</hi> Always provided, the Medicine be a true <hi>Purgative.</hi> But <hi>Horſe</hi>-Phyſick, ſuch as is commonly uſed; I confeſs is too rough and raking, for weak, tender Bodies; and that ſort of <hi>Purging,</hi> makes them more feeble and worſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſuch Caſes (and wanting true <hi>Purgatives</hi>) Phyſicians endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to raiſe up their weak Patients by <hi>Reſtauratives; Jellies, and nouriſhing Broths:</hi> Forgetting the Aphoriſm; <hi>Corpora impura quo plus nutriveris, eo magis laeſeris.</hi> Foul Bodies the more you feed them with high Nouriſhment, the worſe you make them.</p>
               <p>According to the Greatneſs, and Obſtinacy of a Diſeaſe; <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> is to be repeated and continued.</p>
               <p>They that <hi>purge</hi> for <hi>prevention,</hi> and are in a ſeeming indifferent ſtate of Body; need not continue the <hi>Operation</hi> ſo <hi>long</hi> and ſo <hi>often;</hi> as others that are actually <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> and ſuch as have <hi>foul</hi> Bodies.</p>
               <p>Having gone through the ſeveral Stages of this Undertaking; if you look back and review the whole Matter treated; you may plainly perceive the great <hi>Miſtakes,</hi> in the deſigning for, and managing of <hi>Purgation:</hi> Whereby much of the Benefit was loſt, to thoſe that wanted that Help, and had great Expectations from it. I was for ſome Years under the ſame <hi>Miſtake;</hi> being led by <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and impoſed upon by <hi>Authorities</hi> of the Men of great Name, and this Faculty; until ſatisfied otherwiſe, in the <hi>Preparation</hi> of Medicines, and proving their Operations: The only way to have a true Account of the <hi>Virtues,</hi> and <hi>vitious</hi> Properties of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria Medica;</hi> and this gives the trueſt Light, into the Secrets of Curing; and leads the ſafeſt, and neareſt ways to arrive at thoſe deſired Ends: For, without ſuch Knowledge, all the reſt is but a ſpecious vain Pretenſion to Ability; and venturing upon Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, with bold blind Confidence.</p>
               <p>I hear a great noiſe of <hi>Learning,</hi> and Learned <hi>Men;</hi> but I had rather meet with a true Learned <hi>Medicine,</hi> without exception; which as yet I have not; in all the Books I have ſearched; and I have turned over as many Leaves as other Men have done. <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> ſounds great; and indeed true Learning is greatly to be eſteemed; for it is not ſo common, and eaſie to be found, as many do believe: But <hi>Errours,</hi> and <hi>fallacious</hi> Appearances; are more often to be met with; both in <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>Books.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49195:17"/>
               <p>Twenty <hi>Years</hi> and upwards; I ſpent in wading through the vaſt extent of <hi>Phyſick</hi>-Learning; comparing the Sentiments of <hi>Aauthors;</hi> examining their <hi>Medicines,</hi> and proving the <hi>Practice:</hi> And twenty <hi>Years</hi> more, I have laboured to get out of that <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth;</hi> becauſe I do not like it; there's too much to be good; and I ſhould be loth to venture my <hi>Life</hi> with him that knows no better. But if this great <hi>Bulk</hi> of <hi>Learning,</hi> were reform'd, and reduced to a <hi>fourth</hi> Part; the ſuperfluous, and the falſe being cut off; it would be more readily <hi>intelligible,</hi> and much more truly <hi>ſerviceable:</hi> But as it now is; it ſerves <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>'Pothecaries</hi> very well; the Hazards, and the Loſs, falls upon the <hi>Patients.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Great,</hi> and the <hi>Rich,</hi> have their Fate by Phyſick; for they are ſerv'd no better than the meaner ſort; but ſometimes worſe; (I forbear to Name) yet it is commonly ſaid; nothing more could be done, by <hi>Learning,</hi> and Learned <hi>Men:</hi> But if ſuch mortal Caſes, were inquired into; the <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines</hi> examined; I wiſh there were not cauſe to ſay; that more dies by the <hi>Errours</hi> in <hi>Art,</hi> than by the <hi>Defects</hi> of Nature.</p>
               <p>I take my meaſures of Cenſure; not only from the <hi>Miſakes,</hi> and ill Management of <hi>Purgation;</hi> but alſo from the Deficiencies, and Falſities of other conſiderable Parts of this <hi>Learning;</hi> of very ill conſequence in Practice.</p>
               <p>'Tis much eaſier to blind and cheat the Work; than to do a Publick <hi>Good:</hi> For, when many Years have been ſpent, in elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating a Medicine truly <hi>purgative</hi> and <hi>purifying,</hi> to perform the great Work of <hi>Purgation,</hi> as it ought to be done, (ſuch as never came out of a <hi>Shop:</hi>) They <hi>boggle,</hi> are at a ſtand, and take time to conſider, (but not all) that others may try firſt; and make Report: And herein they think themſelves very wiſe and wary; though perhaps in the mean time, they ſuffer by the delay, and want thereof.</p>
               <p>But <hi>virulent</hi> deceitful <hi>Purgatives;</hi> ſuch Stuff as they have been uſed to, (Farriers Phyſick) <hi>that</hi> they can take with confidence, and ſwallow it down freely; when adviſed and adminiſtred in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe</hi>-faſhion; being accounted (by undiſcerning mean Capacities) the Learned way of taking Phyſick: But I account, and well know, that novel <hi>Mode</hi> of Practice to be; <hi>unlearned, unſafe,</hi> and an <hi>unreaſonable</hi> Innovation; for Reaſons exhibited againſt it elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, (<hi>The Practice of Phyſick Reformed,</hi> &amp;c.) not yet anſwered; and probably never will; there is too much Truth to be oppoſed;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49195:18"/>and will abide the Attacks, of all the <hi>Learning,</hi> or <hi>Sophistry;</hi> that can be brought againſt the Validity of thoſe Arguments.</p>
               <p>Much good may do you, with your <hi>Learned</hi> way of taking <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</hi> You may venture ſo as many have done, to their loſs; but I never ſhall, becauſe I know the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainties,</hi> and <hi>Caſualties</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>And here I might juſtly upbraid and deride the <hi>Paeople;</hi> as deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately <hi>ſelf-will'd, praepoſſeſſed, charm'd,</hi> and <hi>Hag ridden</hi> by a <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrum,</hi> the Apparition of feigned Learning. Then let the Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and Head-ſtrong, dote on in a dark, and dangerous Way; ſince Information is vilified, and null'd by Incredulity, and the Vanity of their Imaginations.</p>
               <p>But to wave the extravagant, and pernicious <hi>Mode</hi> of Practice, occurring in our Diſcourſe; and return to the evil <hi>Matter</hi> in Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; our preſent Subject. It ſeems very ſtrange, and looks very ill; that the Operation of <hi>Purging;</hi> ſo efficacious in Preventing, and alſo in Curing Diſeaſes; ſo oft <hi>repeated</hi> in Methods; ſo <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily</hi> required; ſo many <hi>hundred</hi> Years uſed; by <hi>Millions</hi> of People; the Means deſigned, and appointed by the learned Heads in every Age: And yet the Medicines <hi>for</hi> this <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> are not <hi>to</hi> the <hi>Purpoſe;</hi> do not truly anſwer the Intention; but are fallacious and unfit to perform the Work.</p>
               <p>The diſguſting, contaminating, and tabifying <hi>Purges,</hi> that ſtand recorded, and recommended in <hi>Books;</hi> filed in the <hi>Shops;</hi> adviſed, and purchaſed at a good rate; appointed, and falſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſes:</hi> What's all this? but <hi>Shamming</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and <hi>Shameing</hi> the Profeſſion, when it is rightly underſtood: And will then appear a <hi>Blot</hi> upon the Learning, and a <hi>Blemiſh</hi> upon Learned Men: They have ſought for <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Venoms,</hi> where <hi>Purifying,</hi> and healing true <hi>Purgers</hi> are not to be found; deceiving themſelves and others.</p>
               <p>But the People <hi>deſerve</hi> no better; becauſe they <hi>diſcern</hi> no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; they don't diſtinguiſh Men nor Medicines. For <hi>virulent</hi> Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatives, is as acceptable to them; as <hi>Balſamic true Purgatives:</hi> Any ſudden Invention, deviſed upon a bit of <hi>Paper</hi> (cut out for <hi>Shop</hi>-work) from the hands of a conjecturing <hi>Praeſcriber;</hi> is as good to them, or better; than a <hi>Medicine</hi> of <hi>deliberate,</hi> and <hi>ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate</hi> Deſignment; eſtabliſhed by various Probations , and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations, from many Reforms and gradual Improvements, by <hi>Artiſts</hi> of great Induſtry. and Ingenuity in <hi>Pharmacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49195:18"/>
               <p>This I do know, experimentally and ſucceſsfully; that <hi>Purgative</hi> Operation, may be effected (as ought to be) by <hi>Medicine,</hi> wholly conſiſting of what is <hi>amicable,</hi> purely <hi>wholeſom,</hi> and <hi>ſanative:</hi> For ſuch is the <hi>Catholic Medicine;</hi> and like it in <hi>Deſign,</hi> and <hi>Model</hi> of Contrivance; or <hi>equivalent</hi> to it, in <hi>aperitive, abſterſive, purifying</hi> Virtues; or commodious <hi>Properties,</hi> for ready <hi>uſe, portage,</hi> and <hi>duration:</hi> I never met with in all my <hi>reading,</hi> and <hi>ſearch</hi> after what is extraordinary and rare. The <hi>World</hi> was never bleſs'd, with any thing ſo good, for the Purpoſes intended; that I can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of: But this <hi>Help</hi> is hid from their <hi>Eyes;</hi> or barr'd from their <hi>Belief;</hi> that they ſhould wander after mean and hurtful things.</p>
               <p>I was diſſatisfied with the common known <hi>Medicines</hi> extant in <hi>Pharmacopoeia's,</hi> and adviſed in practical <hi>Authors;</hi> thinking much better might be deſign'd, and wrought: Wherein I gave my ſelf more <hi>Trouble</hi> than <hi>Profit;</hi> which Labour and Expence of Time, hath not been recompenſed, and perhaps never will in my Days: But ſome <hi>Perſon,</hi> whom I know not as yet (ſuch are my unhappy Circumſtances) may <hi>reap</hi> what I have <hi>ſown;</hi> and probably to their great Advantage: For this <hi>Product</hi> may endure, and be moſt acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable to the <hi>Generations</hi> to come; and then eſteemed, the choiceſt <hi>Flower</hi> in the Phyſick-<hi>Garden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Streſs of Curing lies <hi>moſtly;</hi> and often <hi>wholly,</hi> upon the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> of Medicine; and Failure moſt frequently, is in the <hi>want</hi> therof. And were the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> ſo fortunately poſſeſſed with wholeſom <hi>true</hi> Medicines; exquiſitely to perform the <hi>Operations,</hi> that Nature requires in order to Curing; (which are not many) they need not then ſpend ſo much Time, about diſputable, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Theorems;</hi> nor burden their Memory, with ſo great a <hi>Syſtem</hi> of Learning. For, the greateſt Difficulties in <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice;</hi> are not the want of knowing what is to be done; as not having, and not truly knowing, wherewith to perform thoſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Intentions that lie fair before them.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>purging</hi> Medicines be not <hi>wholeſom</hi> and <hi>purifying;</hi> but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating and evacuating promiſcuouſly; as before proved: Then they do but palliate and mitigate; by taking away ſome of the old <hi>morbific</hi> Matter, and make <hi>new</hi> ſucceeding Matter: This is deceitful <hi>Purging;</hi> and cauſeth great ſuſpicion upon the reſt, that are ſet forth to perform other <hi>Operations</hi> requiſite in Curing. But it is not my preſent Buſineſs, to examine the other <hi>Claſſes</hi> of the <hi>Materia Medica;</hi> how properly and truly they are regimented and aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49195:19"/>to executed the Offices deſigned for, as by their <hi>Titles</hi> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: That, may require another Undertaking, and is a Work needful; becauſe the <hi>Errours</hi> in <hi>forming</hi> of Medicines are not a few.</p>
               <p>Some of this <hi>Matter,</hi> lay offenſively upon my <hi>Thoughts;</hi> and now being diſcharged thereof, I am at <hi>eaſe;</hi> ſo fare you well, in the way you like beſt.</p>
               <p>Here's <hi>Caution</hi> enough to the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Conſiderate;</hi> and for thoſe that are <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> and undiſcerning; if much more were ſaid, it would be but Labour loſt.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>London,</hi> 1696. in <hi>Grays-Inn-Lane,</hi> by <hi>Kings-Gate.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advert">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Myſtery of <hi>Curing</hi> Comprehenſively; explained and proved <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> and <hi>Practically.</hi> Three Parts. Approved the moſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful, Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,</hi> and <hi>Efficacious</hi> Expedient; againſt ſurpriſing painful <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and ſecret <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays</hi> of Human Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monarchia Microcoſmi.</hi> The <hi>Origin, Viciſſitudes,</hi> and <hi>Period</hi> of Vital Government in Man.</p>
            <p>Enquiries into the general <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Diſeaſes:</hi> Shewing the <hi>Errours,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>The Practice of <hi>Phyſick</hi> Reforme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the <hi>Scurvy.</hi> Another of <hi>Conſumptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory and Myſtery of the <hi>Venereal Lues,</hi> or <hi>Pox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignota Febris.</hi> Fevers miſtaken in <hi>Notion</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The dangerous Tranſition of Pains, to Inflammations, Tumors, Apoſtems, Ulcers, Cancers, Gangrens, and Mortifications, Internal.</p>
            <p>The Ancient and Modern Practice of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> examined and compared.</p>
            <p>The Compleat Phyſician, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Method</hi> and Means, of enjoying <hi>Health, Vigour,</hi> and long <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All writ by the Author hereof.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
